A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Secretary of the Commonwealth, Extradition Requisition and Rendition Files, 2018-2021
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Secretary of the Commonwealth, Extradition Requisition and Rendition Files, 2018-2021
The Library of Virginia
53502
12.95 cu. ft.(37 boxes)
Virginia. Secretary of the Commonwealth.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The records must be reviewed by staff for privacy protected information before serving. Extradition requisition and rendition letters from the Governor(s) may be served, however records including privacy protected information such as social security numbers may not. Privacy protected and confidential information is restricted from public access for 75 years per code of Virginia 42.1-78, 2.2-3800 and 2.2-3705.1-8. Restricted records were not removed from the collection. Types of information and records may include, but are not limited to: social security numbers, Department of Corrections inmate material, fingerprint files, mediation and settlement discussions, and attorney-client privileged material.
Acquisition Information
Transferred on 7 January 2021 from the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, Patrick Henry Building, 1111 East Broad Street, Richmond, VA 23219.
Biographical/Historical Information
The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth has evolved from early colonial times when there existed a Secretary of the Colony. Thomas Nelson held the position of the first Secretary of Virginia in 1776. Early Secretaries were elected by the public. An Act of the General Assembly in 1920 changed the election to a joint vote of the General Assembly. In a 1930 Act the duties of the Secretary were redefined with the Secretary of the Commonwealth serving as the ex officio secretary of the Governor, as custodian of many official State records, and as keeper of the Greater and Lesser Seals of the Commonwealth. The office of the Secretary has gradually acquired other functions, such as: service of out-of-state civil process; appointment and regulation of notaries public; and registration and oversight of lobbyists. The Office became a gubernatorial appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office. The Secretary is appointed by the Governor for a term of four years. Currently the Secretary of the Commonwealth is responsible for gubernatorial appointments, clemency and restoration of civil rights requests and extraditions. Additional activities include: serving as ex officio Secretary to the Governor; serving as keeper of the seals of the Commonwealth; compiling and publishing the annual Blue Book; commissioning and regulating notary publics, including the publication of a Notary Handbook and conduct of disciplinary hearings; promulgating the lobbying disclosure requirements, registration of lobbyists, and recording of lobbying reports; servicing the civil process of out-of-state defendants and other parties; and authenticating and certifying the records of the courts and of any state agency.
Scope and Content
Records, 2018-2021, consisting of extradition requisitions and renditions of the Secretary of the Commonwealth served during the tenure of Governor Ralph Northam (2018-2022). The files are arranged into two series: requisitions and renditions. A requisition documents Virginia's request of another state to return a fugitive to Virginia's jurisdiction. A rendition documents another state's request of Virginia to return a fugitive to the requesting state's jurisdiction. The files are arranged by year and alphabetical therein. The collection is housed in thirty-seven boxes.
A typical requisition file contains an application from the Commonwealth's Attorney, a formal request by the Governor for extradition, and the Governor's request of one or more law enforcement officers to retrieve the fugitive. The Commonwealth's Attorney's application usually includes: copies of the indictment or arrest warrant with supporting affidavits and a statement of facts in support of a Governor's Warrant. Some files include a photograph of the subject of the requisition.
A typical rendition file contains a formal request for extradition from another state's governor, correspondence from the Office of the Attorney General to the Office of the Governor concerning the extradition request, and a copy of the notice of extradition sent by the Secretary of the Commonwealth to the wanted individual. The request for extradition usually includes: copies of the indictment or arrest warrant with supporting affidavits and an appointment of agent by the Governor. Some applications may include a photograph of the fugitive. Also included in each files is a Rendition Fact Sheet completed by the Secretary of the Commonwealth. The Rendition Fact Sheet lists date received, jurisdiction, fugitive's name and address, attorney's name and address, date charged as a fugitive, disposition of fugitive warrant, next scheduled court appearance on fugitive warrant, fugitive status (in custody or out on bond), list of pending Virginia charges and disposition and contact information for requestor.
The records from this collection must be reviewed by staff for personal and medical privacy protected information before serving. Both requisitions and renditions may include privacy protected information such as social security and fingerprints, and case, penitentiary, and arrest records.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I: Requisitions, 2018-2021; and
Series II: Renditions, 2018-2021.
Contents List
- Series I: Requisitions, 2018-2021., Extent: 9.45 cu. ft. (27 boxes) (Box 1-27)
  - 2018
    - A (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Ba (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Be-Bi (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Bl-Bo (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Bra-Bro (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Bro-Bu (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Ca (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Ch-Co (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Cr-Cu (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Da-De (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Do-Du (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - E (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Fe-Fl (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Fr-Fu (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Ga-Gl (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Go-Gra (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Gri-Gu (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Hard-Harr (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Hat-Haz (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - He-Hill (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Hill-Hin (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Ho (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Hu (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - I (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Ja-Je (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Jo (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - K (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - L (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Mc (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Ma-Me (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Mi-Mu (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - N (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - O (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Pa (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Pe-Pl (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Po (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Pr-Pu (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Ra-Ri (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Ro-Ru (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Sa-Sc (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Sh-Si (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Sm-Sp (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - St-Su (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Th (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Th-Ti (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - To-Ty (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - U-V (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Wa-Wh (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Wi-Wy (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - X (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - 2019
    - Ad-Ar (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Ar-Az (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Ba-Be (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Bl-Bra (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Bra-Bu (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Cam-Car (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Cas (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Ch-Cl (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Coa-Con (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Cop-Cr (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Da-De (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Di-Du (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - E (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - F (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Ga-Gl (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Gl-Gu (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Ha (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - He-Hy (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - I-J (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - K (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - La-Li (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Lo-Lu (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Mc (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Ma (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Mi-Moo (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Mor-Mu (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - N (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - O (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Pa-Ph (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Pi-Pre (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Pri-Pu (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Ra-Ri (Box 12, Folder 3)
    - Ro-Ru (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Sa (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Sc-Si (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Sl-Sp (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Ste (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Sti-Sy (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Ta (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Th-Ty (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - V (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Wad-War (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Warr-Wat (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - We-Wi (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Wo-Wr (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Y-Z (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - 2020
    - A (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Ba-Be (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Bi-Bl (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Bo (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Br-Bu (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Bu-By (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Ca-Ch (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Cl-Co (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Cr-Cu (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Da-De (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Di-Do (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - E (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Fa-Fi (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Fl-Fu (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Ga-Go (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Gr-Gu (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Ha (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Hi-Ho (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - I (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - J (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - K (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - L (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Mc (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Ma-Me (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - Mi-Mo (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Mu-My (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - N-O (Box 17, Folder 7)
    - Pa-Pe (Box 17, Folder 8)
    - Pi-Pr (Box 17, Folder 9)
    - Ra-Ri (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Ro (Box 18, Folder 2)
    - Ru (Box 18, Folder 3)
    - Sa-Sc (Box 18, Folder 4)
    - Sh-Sm (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Sm (Box 18, Folder 6)
    - St-Su (Box 18, Folder 7)
    - Ta-Th (Box 18, Folder 8)
    - Th-Tw (Box 18, Folder 9)
    - V (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Wa-We (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Wh-Williams (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Willis-Winstead (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Wo-Wr (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - Y (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - 2021
    - Ab-Ad (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - Ag-Av (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Ba-Bee (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Bel-Ben (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - Bi-Bo (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Bra-Bri (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - Brown (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Bu (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Ca (Box 20, Folder 7)
    - Ch-Cl (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Co (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Cr-Cu (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Dai-Dan (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - Dav-Daw (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Di-Do (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - Du-Dz (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - E (Box 21, Folder 8)
    - Fe-Fl (Box 22, Folder 1)
    - Fo (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - Fr-Fu (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - Ga-Gi (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Go-Gu (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - Ha (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - Hicks-Hill (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Hill (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - Ho (Box 23, Folder 1)
    - Hu-Hy (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - I (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Jackson (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Jam-Jav (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Je-Johnson (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Jones-Josey (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Ka-Ke (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Ki-Ku (Box 24, Folder 1)
    - La-Le (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - Li-Ly (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - McC-McF (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - McK-McW (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - Malloy-Marshall (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - Martin (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - Martinez-Meteku (Box 24, Folder 8)
    - Mi (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Moe-Moon (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - Moore-Morgan (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - Morrell-Muse (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - N-O (Box 25, Folder 5)
    - Pag-Par (Box 25, Folder 6)
    - Pau-Pea (Box 25, Folder 7)
    - Ped-Pet (Box 25, Folder 8)
    - Pi-Po (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - Ra-Re (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - Re (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - Ri-Ro (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - Ro (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Ru (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Sa (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Se-Sh (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Si (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Sl-Sm (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - So-Sp (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - St (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Su-Sw (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - T (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - U-V (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Wa (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - We-Wh (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Wh-Wi (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Wi-Z (Box 27, Folder 9)
- Series II: Renditions, 2018-2021., Extent: 3.50 cu. ft. (10 boxes) (Box 28-37)
  - 2018
    - Ba-Bo (Box 28, Folder 1)
    - Br-Bu (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Ca-Ch (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - Co (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - D-E (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - F (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - G (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Ha (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Ho (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - J (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - K (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - L (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Mc (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Ma-Me (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Mi-Mu (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - N-P (Box 30, Folder 1)
    - Ri (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Ro-Ru (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Sa-Si (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Sm-St (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - To-Tr (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - Wa-We (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Wi-Wy (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Z (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - 2019
    - A (Box 31, Folder 1)
    - Ba-Bl (Box 31, Folder 2)
    - Br (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Ca (Box 31, Folder 4)
    - Ch-Cu (Box 31, Folder 5)
    - E-F (Box 31, Folder 6)
    - Ga-Ha (Box 32, Folder 1)
    - He-Ho (Box 32, Folder 2)
    - Jo (Box 32, Folder 3)
    - Ka-Ke (Box 32, Folder 4)
    - Ke-Ki (Box 32, Folder 5)
    - L (Box 32, Folder 6)
    - Mc-Mu (Box 32, Folder 7)
    - N (Box 32, Folder 8)
    - O (Box 32, Folder 9)
    - R (Box 32, Folder 10)
    - Sal (Box 33, Folder 1)
    - Sau-Saw (Box 33, Folder 2)
    - Sc (Box 33, Folder 3)
    - Sk-Sm (Box 33, Folder 4)
    - Sn-Sy (Box 33, Folder 5)
    - To-Wi (Box 33, Folder 6)
    - Wi-Wo (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - 2020
    - A (Box 34, Folder 1)
    - B (Box 34, Folder 2)
    - Ca (Box 34, Folder 3)
    - Cl-Co (Box 34, Folder 4)
    - D-F (Box 34, Folder 5)
    - G (Box 34, Folder 6)
    - J-L (Box 34, Folder 7)
    - Mc (Box 34, Folder 8)
    - Ma-Mo (Box 34, Folder 9)
    - O-P (Box 35, Folder 1)
    - Ri-Ro (Box 35, Folder 2)
    - Ru (Box 35, Folder 3)
    - Sa (Box 35, Folder 4)
    - Se-St (Box 35, Folder 5)
    - T (Box 35, Folder 6)
    - Wa-Wh (Box 35, Folder 7)
    - Wi-Wo (Box 35, Folder 8)
    - Z (Box 35, Folder 9)
  - 2021
    - A (Box 35, Folder 10)
    - Ba-Bel (Box 36, Folder 1)
    - Ben (Box 36, Folder 2)
    - Bu (Box 36, Folder 3)
    - C (Box 36, Folder 4)
    - D-F (Box 36, Folder 5)
    - G-H (Box 36, Folder 6)
    - I-K (Box 36, Folder 7)
    - L (Box 36, Folder 8)
    - M (Box 37, Folder 1)
    - O-P (Box 37, Folder 2)
    - R (Box 37, Folder 3)
    - S (Box 37, Folder 4)
    - T (Box 37, Folder 5)
    - V (Box 37, Folder 6)
    - W (Box 37, Folder 7)
    - Y (Box 37, Folder 8)